- Even if they wanna cut
down, even if they know
it's killing them, they
find they can't stop.
- My name's Chris Van Tulleken.
I'm an NHS doctor, I'm a scientist,
and I'm part of a growing
group of doctors and academics
who are increasingly
worried about the effect
that the global food
system is having on all of us.
When it comes to
obesity, the way that we've
understood the problem
is it's a failure of willpower.
People are just making bad choices.
They're somewhat lazy.
It's basically their fault.
This is American government data for
men and women of all different ages,
the different lines of
different ages, for obesity.
What you see is between
1960 and 1975, there's a
fairly steady percentage
of obesity in the population.
But in the mid-1970s, obesity starts going
up in all of the groups simultaneously.
Now, if you're saying
willpower is responsible,
what you're proposing
is that all of these groups
of people simultaneously
lost moral responsibility.
And that's not plausible.
Something else happened
to our food in the
mid-1970s to make it
irresistible to people.
My name's John Ruff,
and I've spent 40 years
in the food industry across
seven different countries.
Companies spend a lot of
time optimising all aspects
of their product, the
flavour, the taste, the texture.
People want their product to be as good,
if not better, than the
competitor, so it will sell more.
We use trained sensory
panels to give us ratings.
Is it squishy, is it hard,
is it soft, is it crunchy?
That's very much how
the food industry operates.
One thing many people
don't realise is that factory
processing changes the
textural properties of food.
An interesting fact about soft food
is you're not chewing it as much.
That actually short-circuits
the normal satiety mechanisms
that you would have if you were
actually chewing food properly.
So you're bypassing the normal
mechanism that tells you that you're full.
Once you've worked out that playing around
with the texture of a
food, making it softer,
tricks that normal satiety
or fullness mechanism,
clearly there's an opportunity there
for some kind of scurrilous behaviour
in making food softer so
that people will eat more,
and therefore you sell
more of your product.
So much of the packaged food
that we eat is incredibly soft.
My kids love these.
You don't typically think of
this as being a soft food because
it's a bit crunchy, but
actually after that initial crunch,
you can just crush it
with your tongue, right?
It's got no resistance at all.
But in terms of the calories per gram,
it's got way more calories
than even a very fatty burger.
So the softness and the energy density mean
that you consume it incredibly quickly.
And there's a food industry term
for these very light, puffy
foods that melt in the mouth.
It's called vanishing caloric density.
Gone.
The thing that makes us eat a lot
isn't just what we do to the food.
It's also about logos, marketing, branding,
and understanding the
box the food comes in.
Eating is a multisensory experience.
There's the look of the food.
There's the smell of the food.
There's the feeling of
the food on your fingers.
Even the sound of food matters.
When you open a fizzy
soda, you've got two things.
Two noises.
You've got the click and the tear.
Sound engineers and manufacturers work
really hard to get that sound just right.
And that's sonic branding.
Many companies have asked me
to work on sonic branding for them.
And I think I can mention
when I was working with Kellogg,
they said, "Ooh,
what's sonic branding?
" And I said,
"You invented this.
" Most people will
remember as children
the experience of
lifting a bowl to their ear.
And what are they listening for?
Snap, crackle, and pop.
That's sonic branding at its best.
And that's the original.
There's a lot of competition out there.
And food companies make their money by the
amount of products we consume from them.
So there's a stomach share
that they're fighting for.
And there are hours in the day, in
between breakfast, lunch, and dinner.
What happens between those hours?
They want us to snack.
You wake up and this is what you have.
Snack number one.
Breakfast shake.
Ultra processed.
This is heavily marketed
for you to have on the go.
Do not sit down.
Do not take time to
crunch through something.
Snack number two of the day.
It's empty calories.
Energy dense, nutrient poor.
Every day, you're starting
to get a little bit peckish.
And what do you have?
Veggie straws.
This is a good example of a
health claim snacking product.
Whereas before we would
have had food, actual food,
now we are marketed into believing that
this is actually a healthy replacement.
Some snacking products have now been made
to be linked with being physically active.
So after the gym, I have a
high protein, low sugar bar.
Instead of having a healthier option.
You finish having dinner
and you have these
snacks that are sold
to you as more to share.
Where in fact, you can just finish
them watching the TV by yourself.
I do like them.
I cannot stop eating them.
And I literally can't.
Oh my God.
I think one of the biggest
problems with this kind of food
is that so many of us
struggle to stop eating them.
Hi everyone.
I'm so thrilled to be
here today to speak with
you on my research
that looks at parallels
between addictive substances
and ultra processed food.
When we look at the sorts of foods
that trigger those key
diagnostic indicators
of addiction, it's really
clear what it's not.
It's not minimally
processed foods like fruits or
vegetables or beans or lean
meats like chicken breast.
It's really processed foods.
It's chocolate.
It's ice cream.
It's pizza.
It's foods that don't exist in nature.
The potency and the
reward power of these ultra
processed foods can
trigger an addictive response
that leads them to consume
these in such a compulsive way
that even if they want
to cut down, even if they
know it's killing them,
they find they can't stop.
Imagine you're trying to cut down on ultra
processed food or avoid it altogether.
For a start, it might be the
only food you can afford.
And that is true for millions of people.
But it's everywhere.
And it's engineered and then marketed
by some of the smartest
people on Earth to be irresistible.
So if someone is watching
this and they are struggling
with their weight, with
diet related disease,
I just want to reach out and grab
them and go, this is not your fault.
It is not you.
It is the food.
The Food and Drink
Federation declined our request
for an interview but
provided this statement.
Food and drink manufacturers take
the issue of obesity and poor diets
very seriously, and we
know we have a key role
to play in helping people
to eat balanced diets.
Our members continue to invest
hundreds of millions in pounds
in creating healthier
products for shoppers.
As a result, UK shopping baskets
now contain significantly less salt,
sugar and calories than
they did a decade ago.
Companies are also
working to raise the fibre,
fruit and vegetable
content, of their products.
It's of course up to
government if they want
to introduce new
taxes or warning labels.
However, taxes will
push up the cost of food
and could disincentivise ongoing
investment in healthier products.
We think there are more effective ways
to encourage positive dietary change.
On labelling, we believe
the UK's traffic light system
is a more positive way of nudging
consumers towards healthier choices
than warning labels,
where global evidence
suggests the longer
term impact is limited.
However, we would support a labelling
review, including to test whether consistent,
positive labelling on all healthier
products would help consumers.
The government's Scientific
Advisory Committee on Nutrition
had said there's
insufficient scientific
evidence on the concept
of ultra-processed foods
for it to be used for
dietary guidance or policy
making, and that further
research is needed.
If research comes to light that
processing is a cause for concern,
the food industry will act quickly to
change their ingredients or processes.
Thank you.